James Pike Papers
James Pike Papers
1793-1842
Pike, James, 1777-1842.
0.2 linear ft.
Papers of the American educator, author. James Pike was a New England school teacher and compiler of textbooks. He wrote The Columbian Orthographer (1806) and The Little Reader (1814). Collection includes correspondence (1805-09); diaries (1793-1811); legal papers (1809-1849); school and teaching records (1798-1807); and an undated draft of a constitution for a 'School for Young Ladies.'
149519
Biographical History
James Pike (1777-1842), the son of John and Martha Trevett Pike, was born in Somersworth, New Hampshire, in March 1777. Without doubt he received at least a common school education since he began teaching himself in December 1798. His first school was at Wakefield, Massachusetts, and it was followed by terms at Newbury "Newtown," Salisbury, and Charlestown, Massachusetts, in his home town of Somersworth, New Hampshire, and in the Maine towns in Buxton, Berwick, and Portland. While teaching in Portland he wrote and used in his classroom his spelling book The Columbian Orthographer, which Daniel Johnson published in 1806. The work was sufficiently meritorious that several editions followed.
Pike was in Charlestown, Massachusetts, in 1808-1809, preparing copy and reading proof on a dictionary to be issued by the Charlestown firm of Etheridge & Bliss. If the work was published under Pike's name, no copy seems to have survived. He is known to have published one further school text, The Little Reader, for which the certificate of copyright, 1814, is in the collection. By October of 1812, Pike's eyesight had failed him after many years of eye trouble. Apparently he was not married when his blindness struck, and it is inferred from material in the collection that he was cared for by his family, and that he remained single until his death in 1842 at Somersworth.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James Pike Papers consist of commonplaces, correspondence, diaries, legal papers, miscellaneous writings, and school materials.
Commonplaces consists of eleven items, ten in notebook form, in which Pike or members of his family recorded information from books, newspapers, or other sources to which they wished to refer subsequently. Among them is an index to a "History of the World" compiled by Pike. Correspondence consists of six letters: two outgoing, three incoming, and one to an unidentified publication.
Diaries in the collection cover the period 1793-1811, with some gaps, and for the most part consist of one- or two-line entries largely concerned with the weather. A number of entries, however, are more full, and describe arrivals, departures, and other events, as well as documenting the frequent eye trouble from which Pike suffered. Some vital records of the Pike family and their Somersworth neighbors are also to be found in the diaries.
Legal papers include a series of depositions, a certificate of copyright, a deed, and two receipts. Five items on various topics which may have been written by Pike constitute Miscellaneous writings. Of interest among these is a draft of a constitution for a "School for Young Ladies." The last series, School materials, includes two aids compiled or copied by Pike for use in the instruction of Latin, and a record of the names of his pupils, 1798-1807.
Arrangement of the Collection
School materials are arranged alphabetically by topic. All other material is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Kinsman, Nathan, 1777-1829.; Pike, James, 1777-1842.; Pike, John.; Pike, Nicholas, 1743-1819.; Hastings, Etherbridge & Bliss.; Book industries and trade -- New England.; Commonplace-books.; Education -- Women.; Educators -- Diaries.; Educators -- United States.; English language -- Orthography and spelling.; Latin language -- Study and teaching.; Publishers and publishing -- New England.; Commonplace books.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Authors.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1969.
Inventory
- Commonplaces
  - Undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1805-1809 (Box 1)
    Nicholas Pike to James Pike, 25 Feb 1805
    The Printers (i.e. John M'Kown?) [to James Pike, 1806]
    A Friend to the Ladies, to an unidentified publication [1806?], draft
    James Pike to John Pike, 6 Sep 1806; 20 Jun 1809
    Nathan Kingsman to James Pike, 2 Sep 1807
    [James Pike] to Mr. Bliss, 27 Jun 1808
- Diaries
  - 1793-1794, 1796, 4 items (Box 1)
  - 1799-1801, 1803, 1806, 4 items (Box 1)
  - 1807-1811, 5 items (Box 1)
- Legal papers
  - 1809-1842 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous writings
  - Undated (Box 1)
- School materials
  - Latin teaching aids, undated (Box 1)
  - Record of pupils, 1798-1807 (Box 1)